<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Takes on Zerocchi Blog</title><link>https://blog.zerocchi.com/categories/takes/</link><description>Recent content in Takes on Zerocchi Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:33:45 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.zerocchi.com/categories/takes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>All aboard the (micro)blog train</title><link>https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/08/all-aboard-the-microblog-train.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 13:07:03 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/08/all-aboard-the-microblog-train.html</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/08/all-aboard-the-microblog-train/7bf1cad5dd.jpg" alt="Featured image of post All aboard the (micro)blog train" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;2026 is probably the year I should start writing again, before this ability turning into dust due to English not being my first language and the last time I write long essays/stories was probably around 2016. That&amp;rsquo;s solid 10 years. I chose (micro)blogging because there is no pressure to get everything right and I can better articulate myself. Most importantly, there is no need to fight the mighty algorithms and followers count. It&amp;rsquo;s all freestyle writing here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently got into Indie Web movement where people went back to the original web, the one that corporations played only small part of. Being someone who had a chance experiencing both Old and New webs, I would rather go back to the original web when everything actually have personality and identity. Many people don&amp;rsquo;t realize that their Internet life is dictated by algorithms set by the same five apps they used, as oppose to browsing with intention. I fell into the same trap; I used to mindlessly browsing Instagram reels for hours and sending memes to people. Granted, you get easy dopamine from those activities, but your life will stagnant faster than you thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to reduce as much as possible my screen time on the platforms owned by corporations (i.e. Reddit, X/Twitter, Facebook) and start to actually surf with intentions and discover stuff without mighty al_god_rithms bestowed upon my life. I collected some RSS feeds and started a blog (this one!). I also have personal website at zerocchi.com just to stamp my presence on the small corner of the Internet. I gradually moved away from Google Mail and started using different mail providers. The more you decouple from platforms owned by corporations, the liberating you will feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YouTube and Discord are the only platforms I can&amp;rsquo;t move from yet. There are no solid replacements for YouTube so far, but you can always search videos with intent instead of depending on algorithms to feed content to you. For Discord, as much as I want to use something like IRC, it&amp;rsquo;s probably tricky to ask my buddies to move away as Discord is probably the better IRC. But, I believe the old web will stage a comeback so long the corporations continue to deteriorate their products and offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: I have since moved from micro.blog to somewhere else in order to find a place that fit for me. The general consensus is I will be still blogging in the form of freestyle and sometimes microblogging. I will probably repurpose my micro.blog to something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>