<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Zerocchi Blog</title><link>https://blog.zerocchi.com/categories/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Zerocchi Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:33:45 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.zerocchi.com/categories/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>From zero to IRC server in just a day</title><link>https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/15/064831.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:48:31 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/15/064831.html</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/15/064831/6ce9024d41.png" alt="Featured image of post From zero to IRC server in just a day" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whoops I almost slipped to the realm of not writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can I say.. this past few days I was hyperfixating with IRC, and yesterday alone I spent the entire day setting up a small IRC server for my project circle just for the heck of it because I don&amp;rsquo;t think any sane, normal person will use IRC in this day and age, especially when Discord exist. I&amp;rsquo;m here not to discuss the technical aspect of it, but my experiences setting up these little gremlins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I need to do is to find an IRCd, or what people call IRC daemon. This thing is the one that responsible to implement IRC protocols so that people can talk over the internet. I was looking to install InspIRCd just because it look popular enough, but after a few while I decided against it and proceed to get &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/ngircd/ngircd" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;ngIRCd&lt;/a&gt; instead. The reason being ngIRCd is pretty much a small and simple IRC daemon, unlike &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.inspircd.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;InspiIRCd&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.unrealircd.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;UnrealIRCd&lt;/a&gt; which is quite complex under the hood and are tailored to big servers. But even ngIRCd is pretty tricky to set up the first time. Making it run with Systemd is just very annoying, and it failed to spawn so many times it got me frustrated. Eventually after a few hours I managed to get it to spin together with additional settings like user cloak to hide the IP address attached as hostname. But still, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty lonely since the server is quite barebone. So I decided to install a collection of IRC services that provide you stuff like NickServ, ChanServ and all those server management stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two popular packages, Anope and Atheme. I decided to go with &lt;a class="link" href="https://atheme.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Atheme&lt;/a&gt; because it looks simple and modern enough, although not as popular as Anope. Atheme is even trickier not because it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to set up, it&amp;rsquo;s because I skipped reading docs and just DuckDuckGo-ing my way jumping across Github issues and forum posts to set the thing up. Had I sit down, sip some tea, and went through the docs properly, I&amp;rsquo;ll be done in few minutes. With some luck and patience, the services got through and connected to my server. I just need to attach a few modules afterwards and I already have a collection of Servs at my disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, after wrestling with all the configurations and seemingly hundreds of errors, I finally managed to own a complete small IRC server with all the bells and whistles. I finished them up by getting an IRC bot because what&amp;rsquo;s IRC without all those bots. After few searches I decided on using &lt;a class="link" href="https://limnoria.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Limnoria&lt;/a&gt;, a successor to Supybot. I also set up The Lounge web client so anyone (my friends) without desktop client can join the server easily. The whole process was quite frustrating and fun at the same time and I learnt a lot along the way. Still feel like wanting to try writing IRC bot from scratch so I would have extra goodies for my small server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where is the server, you ask? As this is for my own amusement, I will just keep it to myself and several friends for now. It&amp;rsquo;s public and part of a project I was in, but one needs to know the address to enter and I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone else interested at this point of time. Maybe one day when the project become bigger, people will find out and join the server by themselves. That is if the server is still available at that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/15/064831/6ce9024d41.png"
width="1174"
height="1154"
srcset="https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/15/064831/6ce9024d41_hu_431cb5a65098a18b.png 480w, https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/15/064831/6ce9024d41_hu_631aab4abee60e72.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="The so-called small IRC server"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="101"
data-flex-basis="244px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>PHPfied CSS?</title><link>https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/09/phpfied-css.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 09:21:57 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/09/phpfied-css.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I was this years old to know aside of HTML, you can also convert CSS file to PHP in order to use some PHP shenanigans. Just add a header to indicate that it’s of type &lt;code&gt;text/css&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;div class="chroma"&gt;
&lt;table class="lntable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="lntd"&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;4
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;5
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;6
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;7
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;8
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="lntd"&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-css" data-lang="css"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;php&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;header&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;#34;Content-Type: text/css&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../styles.css?v=&amp;lt;?=filemtime(&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;../&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;styles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;css&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;)?&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;category-header&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;alt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;backdrop-filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;blur&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;and inside the HTML file you can link the stylesheet like usual, except changing the &lt;code&gt;.css&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;div class="chroma"&gt;
&lt;table class="lntable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="lntd"&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="lnt"&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="lntd"&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;rel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;stylesheet&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;href&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;gallery.php&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wild.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>All aboard the (micro)blog train</title><link>https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/08/all-aboard-the-microblog-train.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 13:07:03 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/08/all-aboard-the-microblog-train.html</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.zerocchi.com/2026/01/08/all-aboard-the-microblog-train/7bf1cad5dd.jpg" alt="Featured image of post All aboard the (micro)blog train" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;2026 is probably the year I should start writing again, before this ability turning into dust due to English not being my first language and the last time I write long essays/stories was probably around 2016. That&amp;rsquo;s solid 10 years. I chose (micro)blogging because there is no pressure to get everything right and I can better articulate myself. Most importantly, there is no need to fight the mighty algorithms and followers count. It&amp;rsquo;s all freestyle writing here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently got into Indie Web movement where people went back to the original web, the one that corporations played only small part of. Being someone who had a chance experiencing both Old and New webs, I would rather go back to the original web when everything actually have personality and identity. Many people don&amp;rsquo;t realize that their Internet life is dictated by algorithms set by the same five apps they used, as oppose to browsing with intention. I fell into the same trap; I used to mindlessly browsing Instagram reels for hours and sending memes to people. Granted, you get easy dopamine from those activities, but your life will stagnant faster than you thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to reduce as much as possible my screen time on the platforms owned by corporations (i.e. Reddit, X/Twitter, Facebook) and start to actually surf with intentions and discover stuff without mighty al_god_rithms bestowed upon my life. I collected some RSS feeds and started a blog (this one!). I also have personal website at zerocchi.com just to stamp my presence on the small corner of the Internet. I gradually moved away from Google Mail and started using different mail providers. The more you decouple from platforms owned by corporations, the liberating you will feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YouTube and Discord are the only platforms I can&amp;rsquo;t move from yet. There are no solid replacements for YouTube so far, but you can always search videos with intent instead of depending on algorithms to feed content to you. For Discord, as much as I want to use something like IRC, it&amp;rsquo;s probably tricky to ask my buddies to move away as Discord is probably the better IRC. But, I believe the old web will stage a comeback so long the corporations continue to deteriorate their products and offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: I have since moved from micro.blog to somewhere else in order to find a place that fit for me. The general consensus is I will be still blogging in the form of freestyle and sometimes microblogging. I will probably repurpose my micro.blog to something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>